Atomic Veterans Records MS005
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- Subject files and reports, 1940 -- 2012; MS005.001; 8.6 Linear Feet
  - Radiological Factors Affecting Decision-making in a Nuclear Attack NCRP Report No. 42, 1974; MS005.001.010.00012 (Volume MS005 Shared 1)
  - United States Civil Defense: The Rescue Service, 1951; MS005.001.010.00013 (Volume MS005 Shared 1)
  - United States Civil Defense: The Warden Service, 1951; MS005.001.010.00014 (Volume MS005 Shared 1)
- Audiovisual material and ephemera, 1945 -- 1999; MS005.002; 3.1 Linear Feet; 2 Digital Object(s)
  This series includes photographic prints, slides, audiocassettes, videocassettes and small artifacts related to the United States atomic bomb tests and affected veterans. Photographic prints include black and white images by Jim Lerager, that were probably part of his exhibit on Atomic Veterans, "The Shadow of Death." Also included are four snapshots taken in the Marshall Islands in 1962, a photograph of the wreath lain at Arlington National Cemetery by NAAV in 1994, and an image of a 1946 ship crew. Slides include images of ships from Operation Crossroads arriving at Pearl Harbor in 1946, more Jim Lerager images of veterans, and a photograph of Dr. Sternglass testifying before the U.S. Senate. Videos include documentaries and taped television programs relating to atomic tests. Audiocassettes include amateur tape recordings of veteran's stories, recorded radio and television programs, and a few Marlow interviews with veterans. Audio material includes personal recordings and interviews with veterans. Some audiotapes are from the files that veterans sent to the National Association of Atomic Veterans (NAAV). Many are deeply personal and describe veterans' experiences at atomic tests and the ways in which their involvement effected their lives. Also included are stickers and patches.
  This series is not arranged.
  - Photographs [Pearl Harbor, Bikini Atoll, Christmas Island], 1946 -- 1990; MS005.002.007.00067 (Box 7)
    This folder contains photographic prints and slides. Four snapshots show the
  - Stickers and patches, 1980 -- 1995; MS005.002.007.00068 (Box 7)
    This folder contains one "Atomic Veteran" sticker, one "Radiation Survivor" bumper sticker, and one "Stop Plutonium" patch.
  - Peter Jennings' Downwinders, 1994; MS005.002.008.00001 (Box 8)
    videocassette
  - The American Experience: Radio Bikini, 1988; MS005.002.008.00002 (Box 8)
  - Sleep My Sons: The Story of Arisan Maru, 1996; MS005.002.008.00003 (Box 8)
    The cover of this video is signed by Producer/Director Shawnee Brittan.
  - The Effects of the Atomic Bombs on Hiroshima and Nagasaki, 1945-08-06 -- 1945-08-09; MS005.002.008.00004 (Box 8)
    This video is in Japanese with English subtitles. Daniel A. McGovern's documentary, shot in the days following the attacks.
  - Sandra Marlow: Fernald School Art Exhibit at Boston City Hall [The Effects of the Atomic Bomb on Hiroshima and Nagasaki], 1945; MS005.002.008.00005 (Box 8)
    This video was noted on Marlow's inventory to include footage of an exhibit about the Fernald School at Boston City Hall, but it actually contains the english language version of The Effects of the Atomic Bomb on Hiroshima and Nagasaki.
  - Radiation of the Innocent: Government Guinea Pigs, 1994; MS005.002.008.00006 (Box 8)
    Rolanda show #: RL-031, VTR: 03/03/94. Sandra Marlow's note: Rolonda - TV program in New York.
  - William J. Gaede recording: Operation Castle, 1980; MS005.002.008.00007 (Box 8)
    This tape contains a recording of William J. Gaede from Brighton, Colorado, a Radioman Third Class in the United States Navy stationed at the Eniwetok Atoll during "Operation Castle" in 1954.
    audiocassette; U.S. Navy
  - Eugene P. King recording: Pacific test, 1962, 1982-09-24; MS005.002.008.00008 (Box 8)
    This tape contains a personal interview with Eugene P. King, a member of the United States Navy. He describes his struggle with the medical effects of radiation exposure from 1956 to the time of the recording.
  - James Burke recording: Hiroshima and Nagasaki, 1985; MS005.002.008.00009 (Box 8)
    This tape contains a recording of James Burke, a veteran who served in Nagasaki in 1945. In his statement, he discusses arrival times of United States servicemen in Nagasaki, stating that men aboard the USS Jack Miller arrived as early as September 1945. He also discusses his medical conditions at the time of the interview.
    audiocassette
  - Johnson interview: H-bomb test, 1980; MS005.002.008.00010 (Box 8)
    This tape contains an interview recorded in New Bedford, Massachusetts in 1980 or 1981. The quality of the sound is low, and the content of the tape is difficult to discern.
  - Bill Hoff interview with Jim Dolan: Tales of the H-bomb, 1982; MS005.002.008.00011 (Box 8)
    This tape contains an interview with Bill Hoff who worked in food management at Eniwetok and Bikini Atoll starting in 1955. This tape was recorded in Virginia.
  - Good Morning America: ABC program on atomic tests, 1985; MS005.002.008.00012 (Box 8)
    This tape contains a sound recording of Good Morning America. The quality is low and the audio content of the program is difficult to discern.
  - National Association of Atomic Veterans: First meeting of NAAV women, 1983-05-18; MS005.002.008.00013 (Box 8)
    This is a recording of the first meeting of women members of the National Association of Atomic Veterans, which took place in Washington D.C. in May 1983. There is a duplicate copy, labeled with the same item number, directly behind it in Box 008.
  - Walter Lopes radio interview: National Association of Atomic Veterans, 1982-11-07; MS005.002.008.00014 (Box 8)
    This is a recording of an interview with Walter Lopes for the program, "Let's talk about it now" with George A. Castro on WHIM AM radio in Providence, Rhode Island on the topic of NAAV.
  - History of John L. Thomason, Jr.: Operation Upshot-Knothole, 1983-01-06; MS005.002.008.00015 (Box 8)
    This is a recording of Mrs. Lottie M. Thomas (widow), in Dallas, Texas. She discusses her husband's involvement in Operation Upshot-Knothole (1953) at the Nevada Test site. Her husband retired in 1956 and died in 1959.
  - George Currie interview: Kwajalan Atoll, 1954 [Copy 1], 1985; MS005.002.008.00016 (Box 8)
    In this tape, Sandra Marlow interviews George Currie in Dartmouth, Massachusetts. George Currie, a First Lieutenant in the United States Air Force, was stationed in the Marshall Islands from 1952 to 1954 during the Operation Greenhouse tests.
  - Case history of Lieutenant Colonel Richard I. Matthews, 1985; MS005.002.008.00017 (Box 8)
    This is a testimony for the National Association of Atomic Veterans (NAAV) given by Richard I. Matthews, who served as a radiological safety monitor during Operation Teapot at the Nevada Test site in 1955.
  - Arthur Fortun / Dr. BG Bahne interviews: Operation Crossroads [Copy 1], 1986-04-27; MS005.002.008.00018 (Box 8)
    This is an interview with Arthur Fortun and Dr. BG Bahne, conducted by Sandra Marlow in New Bedford, Massachusetts. Arthur Fortun was a radio operator in the United States Navy during Operation Crossroads in 1946.
  - Arthur Fortun / Dr. BG Bahne interviews: Operation Crossroads [Copy 2], 1986-04-27; MS005.002.008.00019 (Box 8)
  - George Currie interview: Kwajalan Atoll, 1954 [Copy 2], 1985; MS005.002.008.00020 (Box 8)
  - NAAV - late morning, 1983-11-05; MS005.002.008.00021 (Box 8)
  - Fernald State School: Sandra Marlow's interview with school matron Ma Bell, side 1, 1999; MS005.002.008.00022
    This is the first part of Sandra Marlow's interview with "Ma Bell," who worked at the Fernald State School. At the time of the interview, she was the last living matron that had worked at the school. The CD was labeled: Fernald State School History, Sunny Marlow; May Bell side 1.
  - Fernald State School: Sandra Marlow's interview with school matron Ma Bell, side 2, 1999; MS005.002.008.00023
    This is the second part of Sandra Marlow's interview with "Ma Bell," who worked at the Fernald State School. At the time of the interview, she was the last living matron that had worked at the school. The CD was labeled: Fernald State School Sunny Marlow interview; Ma Bell retired matron at the school #2; May Bell side 2.
  - Operation Crossroads Interview: Wanda Seveny, 1981; MS005.002.008.00024 (Box 8)
    This is a recording of an interview of Wanda Seveny, describing her husband's illness to due radiation exposure. Sticker on original case reads: "Crossroads/widow Interview: Wanda Sevnney Seamstress/Portsmouth, RI 1982."
  - Interviews: Sandra Marlow, Walter Lopes, 1984-05-25; MS005.002.008.00025 (Box 8)
    Side 1 contains an interview between Sandra Marlow and Walter Lopes, dated 1984. Side 2 contains Sandra Marlow's (Sunny) narrative of meeting a woman whose children suffered from radiation effects, date unknown.
  - Jim Lerager photographs, 1984 -- 1986; MS005.002.009.00001; Lerager, Jim (Box Shared 44)
    This folder contains three photographic prints from his exhibit, "In the Shadow of the Cloud." These photographs show veterans and families affected by radiation exposure from atomic testing. The families photographed are the Hinkles, the Beamans, and the Dolans. Copyright for these photographs is owned by Jim Lerager.
  - Photograph of Lopsey, Walter Lopes, 1984; MS005.002.009.00002; Converse, Anne T. (Box Shared 44)
    This is a photograph of Walter Lopes, "Lopsey" of Rhode Island, taken by Anne T. Converse of Marion, Massachusetts.
  - Dead things will come from underground drawing, 1970 -- 1995; MS005.002.010.00012 (Volume MS005 Shared 1)
  - A Message For Tomorrow, 1983; MS005.002.010.00013 (Volume MS005 Shared 1)
    A vinyl record (LP 33 1/3rpm) of the song A Message for Tomorrow, composed for the third world congress of the International Physicians for the Prevention of Nuclear War, which occurred in 1983 in Amsterdam. This particular record was published in Japan. Publisher: Hiroshima-Nagasaki Publishing Committee. Composed by Japanese composer Izumi Taku and lyricist Yamakawa Keisuke. The record is scratched slightly.
    phonograph record
- Additional accessions, 1994 -- 2013; MS005.003; 1 Volumes
  - Atomic Veterans Reports and Newsletters, 1994 -- 2013; MS005-001 (Box 1)